# Shana Hutchison

■ 862-226-2764 • Matchis@uw.edu • Inkedin.com/in/shanahutchison

PhD Candidate in Computer Science with research and teaching experience in Data Management. My thesis focuses on building systems with strong mathematical foundations, especially linear and relational algebra. I have since transitioned to a career in industry.

### **Education**

University of Washington

Seattle, WA

Ph.D. in Computer Science & Engineering, M.S. in Computer Science & Engineering (3/2017)

9/2015+

**Awards** NSF Graduate Research Fellow

**Advisors** Bill Howe, Dan Suciu

Stevens Institute of Technology

Hoboken, NJ

M.S. in Computer Science, M.S. in Applied Mathematics, B.E. in Computer Engineering

8/2010-5/2015

**GPA** 4.00 Graduate, 3.97 Undergraduate

**Thesis** ModelWizard: Toward Interactive Model Construction

advised by David A. Naumann, Philippos Mordohai, Andrew D. Gordon

**Awards** 2014 National Barry Goldwater Scholar, Association of Old Crows Scholar, Tau Beta Pi Scholar,

Computing Research Association Outstanding Undergraduate Researcher Honorable Mention

**Societies** Tau Beta Pi (Engineering), Upsilon Pi Epsilon (Computer Science), Eta Kappa Nu (IEEE)

University of Edinburgh

Edinburgh, UK

Study Abroad Semester, 6 courses transferred

1/2014-5/2014

# **Experience**

## **Apache Accumulo** – PMC Committer

Blue Origin – Software Engineer

10/2015+

o Contribute code and discussion to the Apache Accumulo database community

# Laboratory & Industry.....

Kent, WA

Manufacturing Resource Planning Team; Mentor Akira Murphy

11/2021+

- Worked in a Java microservice environment for enterprise systems
- o Investigated a performance regression that resulted in 4 hours of saved processing in a nightly pipeline
- Developed a new full-stack service for monitoring historical pipeline status

Engineering Data Processing Team; Mentor Joseph Schilz

o Developing on a Python web stack that supports analytics for test and flight operations

#### **IBM Research Almaden** – Research Intern

San Jose, CA

SystemML Team; Mentors Matthias Boehm, Alexandre Evfimievski

6/2017-12/2017

- o Developed cost-based optimization for Apache SystemML based on elementary rewrites over sum-product operators
- Achieved speedups as large as 20,000x on machine learning algorithm kernels

### MIT Lincoln Laboratory – Research Engineer

Lexington, MA

Computing and Analytics Group; Advisors Jeremy Kepner, Vijay Gadepally

1/2015-9/2015

- o Engineered Graphulo, a Java server-side matrix math library for the Accumulo database
- Recasted graph algorithms into the GraphBLAS standard; prototyped in Matlab

### Microsoft Research - Research Intern

Cambridge, UK

Programming Principles and Tools Group; Advisor Andy Gordon

6/2014-8/2014

o Designed ModelWizard: a DSL in F# for interactive model construction targeting Tabular, a schema-based probabilistic programming language. Presented a concept poster at the Microsoft PhD Summer School

### Sandia National Laboratories - Technical Intern

Livermore, CA

Information Assurance Group; Advisors Levi Lloyd, Tamara Kolda

5/2013-8/2013

- o Pursued network anomaly detection via Accumulo schemas, machine learning and visualization
- Scaled LXCs (Linux Containers) with MiniMega, a mass distributed VM experiment platform

### MIT Lincoln Laboratory - Research Intern

Computing and Analytics Group; Advisor Jeremy Kepner

**Lexington, MA** 5/2012-8/2012

Bioengineering and Systems Technology Group; Advisor Darrell Ricke

- o Integrated and benchmarked Accumulo distributed database features into D4M,
  - a Matlab package delivering linear algebra and graph theory capabilities via Associative Arrays
- o Applied D4M work to a DNA matching bioinformatics project, published in the Lincoln Laboratory Journal

### Brown Brothers Harriman - Web Development Co-op

Jersey City, NJ

Business Application Development; Advisors John David, Steve Hansen

1/2012-5/2012

o Designed and developed front- and back-end web applications for financial reporting using SQL, C++, and jQuery

Teaching.....

### **University of Washington**

Seattle, WA

Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering: Lecturer

1/2020-3/2020

o CSE 414: Database Systems – taught data management to 150 students as the instructor of record

Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering: Teaching Assistant

9/2018–12/2020,

o CSE 344: Intro to Data Management, CSE 414: Database Systems

4/2020-6/2021

**Stevens Institute of Technology** 

Hoboken, NJ

Computer Science Department: Teaching Assistant

8/2012-12/2013

o CS 506: Intro to IT Security, CS 135: Discrete Structures, CS 334: Automata and Computation

Academic Support Center: Tutor

8/2011-12/2013

o Teach individuals and groups in Mathematics, Computer Science, and Engineering

# **Leadership & Activities**

**Comprehensive Energy Psychology**: Completed CEP level 1, 11/2019.

**Touch for Health Energetic Kinesiology**: Completed training level 1 - 4, 8/2019.

#### UAW 4121, UW's Union of Academic Student Employees:

- Steward for Computer Science & Engineering, 2018–2021
- Chair of Election Committee, 2017–2018

### **Program Committees:**

- o Reviewer for the International Conference on Database Theory (ICDT), 2018
- Reviewer for the Information Systems Journal (Wiley), 2016–2017

Global Grand Challenges Summit: 2017, authored a Top 10 podcast with Sarah Engel on The "Power" of the Internet

▷ https://www.ucl.ac.uk/steapp/professional-education/ggcs-how-to-change-the-world/podcasts/sustainability/sustainability-6

**Undergrad Activities**: Organized seminars as VP of the *Graduate Computer Science Society*; hosted a road race as President of the *Cycling Club*; led operations for the 2012 *Castle Point Anime Convention*, attracting over 2100 people

# **Publications**

partly under former name Dylan Hutchison

## Conference Papers.....

- [C15] Y. R. Wang, S. Hutchison, J. Leang, B. Howe, and D. Suciu, **Spores: Sum-product optimization via relational equality saturation for large scale linear algebra**, *Proceedings of the VLDB Endowment*, vol. 13, no. 11, pp. 1919–1932, Sep. 2020, ISSN: 2150-8097. DOI: 10.14778/3407790.3407799. arXiv: 2002.07951 [cs.DB], Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g-sUU0Xjbrs.
- [C14] M. Boehm, B. Reinwald, D. Hutchison, A. V. Evimievski, and P. Sen, **On optimizing operator fusion plans for large-scale machine learning in SystemML**, *Proceedings of the VLDB Endowment*, vol. 11, no. 12, pp. 1755–1768, Aug. 2018. DOI: 10.14778/3229863.3229865. arXiv: 1801.00829 [cs.DB].
- [C13] H. Jananthan, Z. Zhou, V. Gadepally, D. Hutchison, S. Kim, and J. Kepner, **Polystore mathematics** of relational algebra, in *Big Data*, IEEE, Dec. 2017. DOI: 10.1109/BigData.2017.8258298. arXiv: 1712.00802 [cs.DB].

- [C12] D. Hutchison, Distributed triangle counting in the Graphulo matrix math library, in High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC), IEEE, Sep. 2017. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2017.8091041. arXiv: 1709.01054 [cs.DC], Graph Challenge Honorable Mention; Poster: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/posters/2017-09-Graphulo-TriangleCounting-poster.pdf.
- [C11] L. Milechin, V. Gadepally, S. Samsi, J. Kepner, A. Chen, and D. Hutchison, D4M 3.0: Extended database and language capabilities, in *High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC)*, IEEE, Sep. 2017. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2017.8091083. arXiv: 1708.02934 [cs.DB].
- [C10] D. Hutchison, B. Howe, and D. Suciu, LaraDB: A minimalist kernel for linear and relational algebra computation, in SIGMOD Workshop on Algorithms and Systems for MapReduce and Beyond (BeyondMR), ACM, May 2017. DOI: 10.1145/3070607.3070608. arXiv: 1703.07342 [cs.DB]. Online: https://youtu.be/d-ZY81Is5Pc?t=2m45s, Slides: https://sites.google.com/site/beyondmr2017/program.
- [C9] J. Wang, T. Baker, M. Balazinska, D. Halperin, B. Haynes, B. Howe, D. Hutchison, S. Jain, R. Maas, P. Mehta, D. Moritz, B. Myers, J. Ortiz, D. Suciu, A. Whitaker, and S. Xu, The Myria big data management and analytics system and cloud service, in Conference on Innovative Data Systems Research (CIDR), Jan. 2017. Online: https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~magda/papers/wang-cidr17.pdf, Slides: http://cidrdb.org/cidr2017/slides/p37-wang-cidr17-slides.pdf.
- [C8] D. Hutchison, J. Kepner, V. Gadepally, and B. Howe, From NoSQL Accumulo to NewSQL Graphulo: Design and utility of graph algorithms inside a BigTable database, in High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC), Best Student Paper, IEEE, Sep. 2016. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2016.7761577. arXiv: 1606.07085 [cs.DB], Slides: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/presentations/2016-09-HPEC-Graphulo-Algorithms.pdf.
- [C7] J. Kepner, V. Gadepally, D. Hutchison, H. Jananthan, T. Mattson, S. Samsi, and A. Reuther, Associative array model of SQL, NoSQL, and NewSQL databases, in High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC), IEEE, Sep. 2016. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2016.7761647. arXiv: 1606.05797 [cs.DB].
- [C6] T. Weale, V. Gadepally, D. Hutchison, and J. Kepner, **Benchmarking the Graphulo processing framework**, in *High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC)*, IEEE, Sep. 2016. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC. 2016.7761640. arXiv: 1609.08642 [cs.DB].
- [C5] A. Chen, A. Edelman, J. Kepner, V. Gadepally, and D. Hutchison, **Julia implementation of the dynamic distributed dimensional data model**, in *High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC)*, **Best Paper**, IEEE, Sep. 2016. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2016.7761626. arXiv: 1608.04041 [cs.MS].
- [C4] J. Kepner, P. Aaltonen, D. Bader, A. Buluç, F. Franchetti, J. Gilbert, D. Hutchison, M. Kumar, A. Lumsdaine, H. Meyerhenke, S. McMillan, J. Moreira, J. D. Owens, C. Yang, M. Zalewski, and T. Mattson, **Mathematical foundations of the GraphBLAS**, in *High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC)*, IEEE, Sep. 2016. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2016.7761646. arXiv: 1606.05790 [cs.MS].
- [C3] D. Hutchison, J. Kepner, V. Gadepally, and A. Fuchs, **Graphulo implementation of server-side sparse** matrix multiply in the Accumulo database, in *High Performance Extreme Computing (HPEC)*, **Best Student Paper Finalist**, IEEE, Sep. 2015. DOI: 10.1109/HPEC.2015.7322448. arXiv: 1507.01066 [cs.DB], Slides: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/presentations/2015-09-HPEC-Graphulo-MatrixMultiply.pdf.
- [C2] V. Gadepally, J. Bolewski, D. Hook, D. Hutchison, B. Miller, and J. Kepner, Graphulo: Linear algebra graph kernels for NoSQL databases, in International Parallel & Distributed Processing Symposium Workshops (IPDPSW), IEEE, May 2015. DOI: 10.1109/IPDPSW.2015.19. arXiv: 1508.07372 [cs.DS], Slides: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/presentations/2015-05-GABB-GraphuloInGraphBLAS.pdf.

[C1] D. Hutchison and S. Kleinberg, **Causal inference under uncertainty via adjustments and SOPDs**, in *Causality and Experimentation in the Sciences*, Paris, France, Jul. 2013. Online: http://caeits.sciencesconf.org/conference/caeits/hutchison\_caeits2013.pdf.

# Journal Papers.....

- [J2] M. J. Smith, V. Vaglica, M. Sajeva, N. McGough, D. Hutchison, A. D. Gordon, C. Russo, A. Ramarosan-dratana, and W. Stuppy, Monitoring internet trade to inform species conservation actions, Endangered Species Research, Mar. 2017. DOI: 10.3354/esr00803.
- [J1] J. Kepner, D. Ricke, and D. Hutchison, **Taming biological big data with D4M**, *Lincoln Laboratory Journal*, vol. 20, no. 1, 2013. Online: https://www.ll.mit.edu/publications/journal/pdf/vol20\_no1/20\_1\_6\_Kepner.pdf.

# Thesis....

[T1] D. Hutchison, **ModelWizard: Toward interactive model construction**, M.S. Thesis, Stevens Institute of Technology, May 2015. arXiv: 1604.04639 [cs.PL].

## Book Chapters....

[BC1] V. Gadepally, J. Bolewski, D. Hook, S. Hutchison, B. Miller, and J. Kepner, Graphulo: Linear algebra graph kernels, in *Massive Graph Analytics*, D. Bader, Ed., Taylor & Francis, 2022, ISBN: 9780367464127.

# Preprints....

[U1] D. Hutchison, B. Howe, and D. Suciu, Lara: A key-value algebra underlying arrays and relations, Apr. 2016. arXiv: 1604.03607 [cs.DB].

# Posters...

- [P10] D. Hutchison, M. Boehm, A. Evfimievski, B. Reinwald, P. Sen, and F. Ozcan, Holistic sum-product optimization for large-scale machine learning, Aug. 2017, Poster presented at IBM Intern Symposium.
- [P9] D. Hutchison, B. Howe, V. Gadepally, and J. Kepner, In-database vs. external system analytics on a key-value store, Jan. 2017. Online: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/posters/2017-01-Graphulo-MapReduce.pdf, Poster presented at North East Database Day (NEDB).
- [P8] D. Hutchison, S. Jain, B. Howe, and D. Maier, **Ocean genomic analysis with Myria**, Aug. 2016. Online: https://github.com/uwdb/related-work/blob/master/oceanography-istc/2016-08-Myria-ocean-ISTC.pdf, Poster presented at summit for the Intel Science and Technology Center (ISTC) for Big Data.
- [P7] D. Hutchison, V. Gadepally, J. Kepner, and B. Howe, **Graphulo: Native linear algebra in a NoSQL DB**, Aug. 2016. Online: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/posters/2016-08-Graphulo-algorithms-ISTC.pdf, Poster presented at summit for the Intel Science and Technology Center (ISTC) for Big Data.
- [P6] D. Hutchison, B. Howe, D. Suciu, and Z. Tatlock, **Polystore optimization via program expression graphs**, Jan. 2016. Online: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/posters/2016-01-21-polypeg-poster.pdf, Poster presented at North East Database Day (NEDB).
- [P5] D. Hutchison, J. Kepner, and V. Gadepally, Graphulo: Graph processing for Accumulo databases, Jan. 2016. Online: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/posters/2015-09-Graphulo-ISTC-Poster.pdf, Poster presented at North East Database Day (NEDB) and Sep. 2015 retreat for the Intel Science and Technology Center (ISTC) for Big Data.

- [P4] L. Battle, L. Edwards, V. Gadepally, B. Gavin, B. Hancock, D. Hutchison, J. Kepner, and A. Moran, **Technologies for visualization of big medical text data**, Aug. 2015. Online: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/posters/2015-08-BigDAWG-MIMIC-Topic-Modeling.pdf, Poster presented at Very Large Databases Conference (VLDB).
- [P3] D. Hutchison, E. Cherin, X. Li, and H. Yang, **HBaaS: Heterogeneously-accelerated bioinformatics-as-a-service**, Apr. 2015, Poster and demo presented at Stevens Institute Senior Design Expo.
- [P2] D. Hutchison and the Microsoft Research Tabular Team, **Structural clustering**, Jul. 2014. Online: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/posters/2014-07-structural-clustering.pdf, Poster presented at Microsoft PhD Summer School.
- [P1] D. Hutchison and D. Kleszyk, **Investigating the influence of infrastructure on the load response of stevens course servers**, Dec. 2011, Course project for CPE 345 Modeling and Simulation.

# Other Talks and Demos.

- [O13] D. Hutchison, **Smart contracts**, Jan. 2018. Online: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GMYkt7Rhmcg, UWDB Seminar; Slides: http://bit.ly/2DG9k87.
- [O12] D. Hutchison and M. Ahmad, **SystemML: Large-scale ML, DL, and optimization**, Oct. 2017, UWDB Seminar.
- [O11] D. Hutchison, Holistic sum-product optimization for large-scale machine learning, Aug. 2017, IBM Project Presentation.
- [O10] —, In-database analytics for NoSQL key-value stores, Dec. 2016. Online: https://www.cs. washington.edu/qualsexam/dhutchis, Slides: https://github.com/Accla/graphulo/blob/master/docs/presentations/2016-12-KeyValue-Analytics.pdf.
- [O9] B. Howe, D. Hutchison, and S. Jain, **Demo of myria as a federated database**, Oct. 2016. Online: https://github.com/uwescience/raco/blob/SPJA\_federation/HPDA\_review.ipynb, Presentation and demo to government sponsors.
- [O8] D. Hutchison, J. Kepner, and V. Gadepally, Lara: A language of linear and relational algebra for polystores, Dec. 2015. Online: http://db.cs.washington.edu/events/database\_day/2015/ database\_day\_2015.html, UWDB Database Day industry talk.
- [O7] —, **Graphulo use and design**, Aug. 2015, Presentation and demo to government sponsors.
- [O6] V. Gadepally, L. Edwards, D. Hutchison, and J. Kepner, **Using d4m for rapid prototyping of analytics for apache accumulo**, Apr. 2015. Online: http://accumulosummit.com/program/talks/using-d4m-for-rapid-prototyping-of-analytics-for-apache-accumulo/, Presentation at Accumulo Summit.
- [O5] D. Hutchison, A. Gordon, and C. Russo, ModelWizard: Interactive model construction for Tabular, Aug. 2014. Online: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/presentations/2014-08modelwizard-tabular.pdf, Presentation and demo to Programming Principles and Tools at Microsoft Research.
- [O4] D. Hutchison and L. Lloyd, **Network anomaly detection**, Aug. 2013. Online: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/presentations/2013-08-network-anomaly-detection.pdf, Presentation at an intern symposium at Sandia National Laboratories.
- [O3] D. Hutchison, **Our aims as modelers: Toward better predictions, explanations, interventions**, Aug. 2013. Online: github.com/dhutchis/ModelTalk, Presentation at a technical seminar at Sandia National Laboratories.
- [O2] —, Uncertain? Represent your belief with SOPD, Jan. 2013. Online: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/presentations/2013-01-omm-sopd.pdf, Minute madness talk at Programming Languages Mentoring Workshop (PLMW) at the Principles of Programming Languages Conference (POPL).

[O1] —, Accelerating bioinformatics with big data technologies, Aug. 2012. Online: https://github.com/dhutchis/documents/blob/master/presentations/2012-08-d4m-bioinformatics.pdf, Presentation at an intern symposium at MIT Lincoln Laboratory.